Register of the Socialist Workers Party Records, 1928-1990
Hoover Institution Archives
Socialist Workers Party Records,
1928-1990
92036
Socialist Workers Party
111 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box 47.2 linear feet
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, minutes, resolutions, theses, and internal bulletins, relating to Trotskyist and other socialist activities in Latin America, Western Europe, Iran, and elsewhere, and to interactions of the Socialist Workers Party with the Fourth International; and trial transcripts, briefs, other legal documents, and background materials, relating to the lawsuit brought by Alan Gelfand against the Socialist Workers Party in 1979..
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1992.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Most of collection also available on microfilm (107 reels).
Access Points
Fourth International.; Socialism.; Communism.; Communism--United States.; Communism--Latin America.; Communism--Europe.; Communism--Iran.; Socialism--United States.; Socialism--Latin America.; Socialism--Europe.; Socialism--Iran.; United States--Politics and government.; Latin America.; Europe.; Iran.; Gelfand, Alan.
Historical Note
The Socialist Workers Party had its origins in the Communist League of America, formed in 1928 by former members of the Workers (Communist) Party of America who had been expelled as followers of Leon Trotsky. The Communist League of America merged with the American Workers Party in 1934 to create the Workers Party of the United States. This organization dissolved in 1936 to allow its members to enter the Socialist Party, where they constituted a left wing. Members of the left wing, after expulsion from the Socialist Party, founded the Socialist Workers Party at the beginning of 1938.
From its outset as the Communist League of America, the Socialist Workers Party viewed itself as the American section of an international left wing of the communist movement whose outstanding leader was Leon Trotsky. This current first found organizational expression as the International Left Opposition in 1930. A belief that the program and practices of the Communist International were in need of drastic reform gradually gave way to the conviction that that organization was incorrigible and should be supplanted. The course of this progression of thought is indicated by the transformation of the International Left Opposition into the International Communist League in 1933 and then into the Movement for the Fourth International in 1936. The Fourth International was established in 1938 with the proclaimed goal of serving as the world party of socialist revolution.
World War II disrupted the workings of the Fourth International and many of its sections. A European Secretariat in exile functioned in the United States during the war. The passage in 1940 of the Voorhis Act, which required parties belonging to any international political organization to register with the United States government and provide lists of members and contributors, prompted the Socialist Workers Party to formally disaffiliate from the Fourth International. When the International resumed its operations after the war, the party maintained a close relationship with it and was recognized as a fraternal organization but never formally rejoined as its American section.
Political differences within the Fourth International resulted in a rupture in 1954. Most of the continental European sections adhered to the orientation of the International Secretariat, the International's continuing directing body. The Socialist Workers Party aligned itself with some other sections in establishing a rival International Committee. For all practical purposes Fourth International (International Secretariat) and Fourth International (International Committee) operated as separate organizations. Unity of most forces on both sides was restored in 1963, with a newly created United Secretariat as continuing directing body.
Rupture again threatened but was averted in the 1970s. The Socialist Workers Party aligned itself with a number of Latin American sections in creating a Leninist-Trotskyist Tendency (subsequently Leninist-Trotskyist Faction) within the International in 1973. This was opposed by an International Majority Tendency representing most of the European sections. The factions were dissolved in 1977.
The Socialist Workers Party found itself increasingly in disagreement with the Fourth International in the 1980s as the party ceased to define itself as Trotskyist. The Fourth International meanwhile accorded recognition to two organizations originating in splits from the party, Socialist Action and the Fourth Internationalist Tendency, as sympathizing American sections in addition to the Socialist Workers Party. The 12th World Congress of the Fourth International in 1985 was the last in which representatives of the Socialist Workers Party participated. Since the party was not formally a member of the Fourth International the question of formal withdrawal did not arise. However by the end of the decade the Socialist Workers Party had broken off all connections with the Fourth International.
Scope and Content
Records of the Socialist Workers Party are deposited at the Wisconsin State Historical Society as well as in the Hoover Institution Archives. Those at the Wisconsin State Historical Society are concerned with domestic activities of the party, while those in the Hoover Institution Archives are concerned with its international activities and especially with its relations with the Fourth International and its predecessors.
Records in the Hoover Institution Archives are arranged in nine series, most of which call for some commentary. Fourth International Issuances, the first series, consists of official issuances, notably minutes, congress proceedings, and internal bulletins, of the Fourth International and its predecessors. Issuances of international bodies only, not national sections, are included. These are arranged by issuing bodies, which are listed in order of historical progression. Issuances lend themselves to serial arrangement and are listed in considerable detail.
The next two series, Chronological File and Geographical File, are extremely rich but much more amorphous. Correspondence between Socialist Workers Party leaders and Fourth International leaders, reports and memoranda of all descriptions, and official and unofficial documents of all sorts emanating from practically every national section are included. Materials within the two files are similar in character and many documents might with equal validity have found their way into either. Individual folders as maintained by the Socialist Workers Party and the Library of Social History (where the records were held prior to their deposit in the Hoover Institution Archives) tended to be established and assigned headings according to criteria that were either chronological or geographical. These classificatory decisions were respected and the two series were constructed by grouping folders together according to which of the two criteria they met. Arrangement of the material within each was then regularized. It is important for researchers interested in a particular geographical area to keep in mind that the Chronological File as well as the Geographical File is likely to include relevant material. An attempt has been made to annotate the Chronological File listings with indications of concentrations of material relating to specific countries, but such annotations are by no means exhaustive. Official issuances of national sections lending themselves to serial listing are generally specified. Other materials are generally not itemized, not because their importance is less but because a rigorously itemized list would be of prohibitive length.
The International Assignments File consists of correspondence and reports of Socialist Workers Party representatives abroad on international assignments, mainly during the 1970s.
The Barnes/Waters File is drawn from the papers of Jack Barnes and Mary-Alice Waters, leaders of the Socialist Workers Party and its principal representatives in dealings with the Fourth International during the 1970s and 1980s. Arranged chronologically by congresses and other meetings of the Fourth International, it is a major source for activities of the International during those decades and includes much material, especially minutes and world congress proceedings, that might otherwise have been included in the Fourth International Issuances series.
The Leninist-Trotskyist Faction File consists of internal circulated materials documenting the history of the international Leninist-Trotskyist Faction (described in the Historical Note above) during the period of its existence from 1973 to 1977.
The Gelfand vs. Smith et al. File requires special explanation. The Workers Revolutionary Party and the Workers League, Trotskyist organizations in Great Britain and the United States respectively that remained outside the Fourth International (United Secretariat), embarked in 1975 upon a series of allegations that Soviet secret police and United States Federal Bureau of Investigation penetration of the Socialist Workers Party beginning in the 1930s had turned that party into one that was police-controlled. These allegations were characterized by the Socialist Workers Party, and by a number of unaffiliated observers, as a slander campaign. Alan Gelfand, an expelled member of the Socialist Workers Party, initiated a lawsuit in 1979 against leaders of the party and leading law enforcement officials of the United States government on the basis of these allegations. The case went to trial in federal district court in 1983 and resulted in judgment against Gelfand. This series contains not only the legal records of the Socialist Workers Party defendants in the trial but also extensive background material on the allegations and their history.
Container List
- FOURTH INTERNATIONAL ISSUANCES, 1930-1990. (Box No. 1-14, 54-56)
  Official issuances of international bodies of the Fourth International and its predecessors. Arranged by issuing body.
  - International Left Opposition. International Secretariat (Box 1.)
    - Bulletin International
      - 1930. No. 1 (late August) (Folder 1)
      - 1931. No. 6 (April), no. 8 (June) (Folder 2)
      - 1933. No. 2/3 (April), no. 4 (late May) (Folder 3)
    - Internationales Bulletin
      - 1931. No. 6 (April) (Folder 4)
      - 1932. No. 16 (May) (Folder 5)
    - Minutes
      - 1930. April 6, December 1, 14 (in French) (Folder 6)
      - 1931. February 17, 24, March 3, 9-10, 31, April 7, 14, 18, May 10, 12, 19, 31, June 9, 16, 26, July 2, 12, 16, 19, 30, August 9, 13, 20, 25, September 3-4, 6-7, 13, 23, 25, September 30-October 1, October 4, 8, 13, 22, 29, November 2, 8, 10, December 21 (in French and English) (Folder 7)
      - 1932. February 7, May 2, 24, June 3, 9, 22, 29-30, July 16, 23, August 11-12, 23, December 15 (in French and English) (Folder 8)
  - International Communist League. Conference, 1933 February 4. Reports (Folder 9)
  - International Communist League. Commission Centrale Internationale des Jeunes. Includes correspondence and other papers of Albert Glotzer as participant in work of the Commission
    - 1930-1933. Correspondence (Folder 10)
    - 1934. Correspondence, resolutions, declaration, and reports. Includes documents of International Youth Conference of February 28 (Folder 11)
    - 1935-1936. Correspondence. Includes Internationales Jugend-Bulletin No. 2 (1936 late March) and no. 3 (June); and Internationale Jugendinformation(1936 late May) (Folder 12)
  - International Communist League. International Secretariat
    - Bulletin [French]
      - 1933. No. 1 (late October), no. 2 (late November) (Folder 13)
      - 1934. No. 3 (January), no. 4 (June, including typed English translation) (Folder 14)
      - 1935. No. 1 (May 1), no. 2 (June 1), unnumbered (July), no. 4 (September 1), no. 5 (October), no. 6 (December) (Folder 15)
      - 1936. No. 7/8 (May) (Folder 16)
    - Bulletin [German]. New series, no. 1 (1934 late January) (Folder 17)
    - Bulletin d'Information et de Presse sur l'URSS. No. 1 (1936 January), no. 2/3 (May)1936 (Folder 18)
    - Bulletin Intérieur. No. 1 (1935 April), no. 2 (May), no. 3 (September)1935 (Folder 19)
    - Documents et Discussions. No. 1 (1934 early January) (Folder 20)
    - Dokumente. Unnumbered (1935) (Folder 21)
    - International Bulletin. New series, no. 1 (1934 April), no. 2 (September) (Folder 22)
    - Minutes (Box 2.)
      - 1933. May 22, August 24, October 11, November 9, 13, 17-19 (in French, English and German) (Folder 1)
      - 1934. February 22, April 27, June 2, 9, 12 (in French and English) (Folder 2)
      - 1935. March 19, June 3, 10, 15, July 12, 22, 29, August 5, 10, September 16, 23, October 2, 9, 16, 23, 30, November 6, 13, 19 (in French) (Folder 3)
      - 1936. January 8, 16, February 8, 14, March 13, 15 (in French) (Folder 4)
    - Mitteilungen der Bolschewiki-Leninisten. No. 2 (1933 mid-November) (Folder 5)
    - Press Service. Unnumbered (1935 August) (Folder 6)
    - Service de Presse. Unnumbered (1935 July 1) (Folder 7)
    - Service d'Information et de Presse. No. 1 (1936 June 12), no. 3 (July 4), no. 4 (July 20)1936 (Folder 8)
  - International Communist League. International Secretariat. Deutsche Kommission. Minutes. 1935 July 19, 24-25, August 1, 10, 16 (in German) (Folder 9)
  - Movement for the Fourth International. Conference, 1936 July 29-August 1. Theses, resolutions and appeals (Folder 10)
  - Movement for the Fourth International. International Secretariat
    - Bulletin Intérieur International. No. 1 (1937 April) (Folder 11)
    - Information Bulletin. Unnumbered (1937 July) (Folder 12)
    - International Internal Bulletin. No. 2 (1938 April) (Folder 13)
    - Minutes
      - 1936. December 13 (in French) (Folder 14)
      - 1937. January 5, 12-13, February 20, March 7, April 17, May 15, July 3, 10-11, August 28, October 21, 29, November 2, 8, 17, December 5 (Folder 15)
      - 1938. January 23 (Folder 16)
    - Press Information Service. Unnumbered (1937) (Folder 17)
    - Service d'Information et de Presse
      - 1936. No. 5 (August 11), no. 6 (August 22), no. 7 (September 4), no. 8 (September 13), no. 9 (September 20), no. 10 (September 27), no. 11 (October 2), no. 12 (October 21), no. 13 (November 4), no. 14 (December 1), no. 15/16 (December 20) (Folder 18)
      - 1937. No. 17 (February 22), no. 18 (March 16), no. 19/20 (June), no. 21/22 (early August) (Folder 19)
  - Movement for the Fourth International. International Youth Secretariat. Bulletin International
    - 1937. Unnumbered (November 10) (Folder 20)
    - 1938. No. 3 (February) (Folder 21)
  - Fourth International. Statutes, 1938, 1947 (draft), 1948, 1969, 1970, 1974 (in French and English) (Folder 22)
  - Fourth International. World Congress (1st), 1938 September 3. Minutes, and memoir by Charles van Gelderen (Folder 23)
  - Fourth International. Emergency Conference, 1940 May. Agenda, preparatory material, resolutions, reports and manifesto (Folder 24)
  - Fourth International. Conference, 1946 April. Minutes, reports, resolutions and manifesto (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - Fourth International. World Congress (2nd), 1948 April 2-21. Reports, resolutions, manifesto and informational bulletin (Folder 2)
  - Fourth International. World Congress (3rd), 1951. Resolutions (in Spanish) (Folder 3)
  - Fourth International. World Congress (5th), 1957. Resolutions (Folder 4)
  - Fourth International. World Congress (6th), 1961. Resolutions (Folder 5)
  - Fourth International. World Congress (7th, Reunification), 1963. Minutes, and SWP resolution on reunification (Folder 6)
  - Fourth International. World Congress (8th), 1965
    - Minutes (in English and French) (Folder 7)
    - Reports (in English and French) (Folder 8)
    - Draft resolutions (in English and French) (Folder 9-10)
  - Fourth International. World Congress (9th), 1969 (Box 4.)
    - Minutes (Folder 1)
    - Reports and summaries of proceedings (in English and French) (Folder 2)
    - Resolutions (draft and final, in English and French) (Folder 3)
    - Background material. Reports on Ligue Communiste of France (Folder 4)
  - Fourth International. World Congress (10th), 1974. Minutes and reports (Folder 5)
  - Fourth International. World Congress (11th), 1979 (Box 54.)
    - Minutes (Folder 1)
    - Resolutions and reports
      - English versions (Folder 2)
      - French versions (Folder 3)
      - Spanish versions (Folder 4)
  - Fourth International. World Congress (12th), 1985
    - Minutes (Folder 5)
    - Resolutions
      - English versions (Folder 6)
      - French versions (Folder 7)
  - Fourth International. World Congress (13th), 1990. Draft resolutions (Folder 8)
  - Fourth International. All-American Bureau. Minutes. 1939 March 1, 8 (Box 4., Folder 6)
  - Fourth International. All American Pacific Bureau. Minutes. 1938 May 17, 19, July 6. Includes resolutions (Folder 7)
  - Fourth International. Departamento Latino-Americano
    - Boletín de Información
      - 1938. No. 1 (July), no. 2 ( September), no. 3 (October), no. 4 (n.d.) (Folder 8)
      - 1939. No. 5 (May), no. 6 (September), no. 7 (November) (Folder 9)
      - 1940. No. 8 (October) (Folder 10)
      - 1941. No. 12 (November) (Folder 11)
    - Boletín Informativo Latino-Americano. Vol. 1 no. 1 (1949 March) (Folder 12)
  - Fourth International. Secretariado Latinoamericano. Boletín Internacional. No. 1 (1959 January) (Folder 13)
  - Fourth International. Ecole de Cadres Internationale. Syllabus. 1952 April (in French) (Folder 14)
  - Fourth International. European Secretariat
    - Bulletin (in French)
      - 1944. Unnumbered (n.d.), no. 2 (December) (Folder 15)
      - 1945. Unnumbered (January), no. 3 (February), no. 7 (August) (Folder 16)
    - Minutes. 1945 July 17, 24, 31, August 7, 14, 21, 28, September 4, 11, 18, 25, October 2, 10, 16, November 12, 17, 26, December 1, 4 (in French and English) (Folder 17)
  - Fourth International. International Executive Committee (Box 5.)
    - Fourth International. Unnumbered (1955) (Folder 1)
    - International Bulletin
      - 1940. Vol. 1 no. 1 (July) (Folder 2)
      - 1941. Vol. 1 no. 6 (July) (Folder 3)
      - 1942. Vol. 2 no. 1 (April), no. 3 (September) (Folder 4)
    - Minutes. Includes agenda, reports, resolutions and declarations (in English and French)
      - 1939
        - September 12 (Folder 5)
        - September 21 (Folder 6)
        - November 1 (Folder 7)
      - 1946 June (Folder 8)
      - 1947
        - March (Folder 9)
        - September 10-19 (Folder 10)
      - 1948
        - February 9-13 (Folder 11)
        - October 9-12 (in French) (Folder 12)
      - 1950
        - April-May (Folder 13)
        - December (Folder 14)
      - 1952
        - February (Folder 15)
        - November 15 (Folder 16)
      - 1953
        - May 9-11 (Folder 17)
        - December 26-28 (Folder 18)
      - 1962 June 23-24 (Folder 19)
      - 1964 May (Folder 20)
      - 1965
        - January 1-3 (Folder 21)
        - July 23-25 (Folder 22)
      - 1966 July 2-3 (Folder 23)
      - 1967 March 10-12 (Folder 24)
      - 1968 February (Folder 25)
      - 1969
        - April 20 (Folder 26)
        - December 22-25 (Folder 27)
      - 1970 December (Folder 28)
      - 1971 October 29-November 1 (Folder 29)
      - 1972 December 2-6 (Folder 30)
      - 1974 February 15 (Folder 31)
      - 1975 January 27-30 (Folder 32)
      - 1976 February 12-15 (Folder 33)
      - 1979 November 18 (Box 55., Folder 1)
      - 1981 May 7-14 (Folder 2)
      - 1982 May 22-30 (Folder 3)
      - 1985. January 27, February 6 (Folder 4)
      - 1986 February 23-March 2 (Folder 5)
      - 1987 June 22-28 (Folder 6)
      - 1988 December 3-10 (Folder 7)
  - Fourth International. International Secretariat (Box 6.)
    - Boletín Interno
      - 1951. Unnumbered (September) (Folder 1)
      - 1962. Unnumbered (July) (Folder 2)
      - 1963. Unnumbered (n.d.) (Folder 3)
    - Bulletin d'Information
      - 1952. Unnumbered (November 1) (Folder 4)
      - 1962. No. 5 (March), no. 6 April), no. 8 (September) (Folder 5)
    - Bulletin Intérieur
      - 1946. Vol. 1 no. 1 (May), no. 2 (May), no. 3 (May), no. 4 (July), no. 5 (August), no. 6 (September), no. 8 (October), no. 9 (November), no. 10 (December) (Folder 6)
      - 1947. Vol. 1 no. 11 (January); vol. 2 no. 12 (February); vol. 1 [sic] no. 13 (March); vol. 2 no. 14 (April), no. 15 (June), no. 16 (July), no. 17 (August), no. 18 (September), unnumbered (October), unnumbered (December) (Folder 7)
      - 1948. Unnumbered (November) (Folder 8)
      - 1949. Unnumbered (February), two unnumbered (May), unnumbered (October), unnumbered (November), three unnumbered (December) (Folder 9)
      - 1950. No. 1 (February), no. 2 (April), unnumbered (May 4), unnumbered (June), no. 5 (October) (Folder 10)
      - 1951. No. 1 (January), no. 2 (February), no. 3 (March), no. 4 (April), no. 5 (May), no. 6 (June), no. 8 (July), four unnumbered (September), unnumbered (December) (Folder 11)
      - 1952. No. 2 (March), no. 3 (April), no. 4 (May), no. 6 (July), unnumbered (October) (Box 7., Folder 1)
      - 1953. No. 1 (January), no. 2 (January), no. 3 (February), no. 4 (April), unnumbered (April), no. 5 (May), no. 6 (July), unnumbered (October, including typed English translation), unnumbered (November), unnumbered (December) (Folder 2)
      - 1954. Unnumbered (January), unnumbered (February), unnumbered (March), unnumbered (October) (Folder 3)
      - 1955. No. 7 (November) (Folder 4)
      - 1956. Unnumbered (April, including holograph English translation), unnumbered (November) (Folder 5)
      - 1957. Unnumbered (February, including typed English translation), unnumbered (March), unnumbered (July), unnumbered (November) (Folder 6)
      - 1959. Unnumbered (January), no. 2 (June) (Folder 7)
      - 1961. Unnumbered (December) (Folder 8)
      - 1962. No. 2 (February), unnumbered (March), no. 7 (May), no. 9 (June), no. 13 (July), no. 14 (July), no. 15 (August), no. 16 (August), no. 17 (August), no. 18 (August), no. 19 (September), no. 20 (October), no. 23 (October), no. 27 (November) (Folder 9)
      - 1963. No. 31 (February), no. 33 (February, hand-corrected from no. 4), no. 35 (February), no. 36 (April), no. 37 (April), no. 38 (April) (Box 8., Folder 1)
    - Bulletin International. No. 1 (1938 August) (Folder 2)
    - Information Bulletin. 1959 Vol. 1 no. 21 (January 1), no. 22 (January 15), no. 23 (February 1), no. 24 (February 15), no. 25 (March 1), no. 26 (March 15), no. 27 (April 11); vol. 2 no. 1 (April 11), no. 2 (May 1), no. 3 (May 15), no. 4 (June 1), no. 5 (June 15), no. 6 (July 1, hand-corrected from no. 5), no. 7 (July 15), no. 8 (August 1), no. 9 (August 15), no. 10 (September 1), no. 11 (September 15), no. 12 (October 3), no. 13 (October 18) (Folder 3)
    - Internal Bulletin